<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>DevConf.CZ Blog</title>
    <link href="/blog" />
    <link type="application/atom+xml" rel="self" href="/cz/blog/feed.atom" />
    <updated>2022-05-05T09:35:56+00:00</updated>
    <id>/cz/blog/feed.atom</id>
    <author>
        <name>Josef Ridky &lt;jridky@redhat.com&gt;</name>
    </author>
                <entry>
    <id>/cz/blog/first-time-speaker-at-devconf</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="/cz/blog/first-time-speaker-at-devconf" />
    <title>First-time speaker at DevConf? 7 tips to increase confidence and calm your nerves before speaking! </title>
    <published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Radek Vokal</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">I still remember my first time speaking at a conference. I was extremely nervous, I skipped a few things I wanted to mention and at the end of it, I wasn’t sure if the audience even got what I wanted to share. But then I was approached by my colleagues......</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p>I still remember my first time speaking at a conference. I was extremely nervous, I skipped a few things I wanted to mention and at the end of it, I wasn’t sure if the audience even got what I wanted to share. But then I was approached by my colleagues and even by random folks from the audience asking me questions about the talk. It felt great that I was heard and I got someone else interested. </p>
<p>Over the years, I spoke at many other events and conferences. I still feel nervous when presenting, but I learned a few techniques and habits that make me feel more confident and comfortable in speaking. Before I share these, there’s one important thing to mention first. Practice makes perfect and there’s no better way to gain credibility and authority in the project or your expertise than by speaking at conferences. By giving talks at various conferences, you position yourself as a trusted person who understands the topic, is able to research existing and new things, and adds value and his personal experience to the subject. This is the way you’ll gain trust, respect, and authority in your field of expertise. </p>
<p>Well, despite these benefits of speaking at a conference, there’s still the main problem - the fear and uncertainty that you’ll be able to deliver a great talk. Speaking publicly in front of a large audience or even virtually makes us vulnerable. We’re on the spot, visible to a large number of people, some of them have better knowledge about the subject than we have, you are the center of attention but you also need to maintain that attention and make sure you don’t lose the audience. Many of us don’t present in our native language, to an audience that is international and diverse. This all adds up to a fear that stops from stepping up and presenting. </p>
<p>Here are some of my tips that help me be prepared and less nervous. </p>
<h2>#1 Rehearse with a mirror,  record yourself</h2>
<p>Most people don’t like this one. Watching yourself on video, listening to your own voice or even seeing yourself in a mirror while talking feels awkward. But it’s important to see how you appear in front of your audience. Your body language shows a lot about your confidence and often we don’t notice our bad habits until we observe ourselves. You’ll get used to the sound of your voice and you’ll experience how others hear you. You might have a filler word you use way too often or something in your body language that is disrupting and watching yourself will allow you to spot it and avoid it. It will help you to realize what your pace is and if you should slow down. </p>
<h2>#2 Rehearse in a smaller group, with colleagues, friends</h2>
<p>The best way to practice your speaking is to rehearse with a smaller group. This can be your colleagues at work, friends or family, or even local Toastmasters groups. The only way to get better with your talk is to present often and preferably in an environment where you’ll be able to get a lot of feedback. Toastmasters are great since their main focus is on how you speak and how you use your body language. Also, you’ll be able to get feedback on the structure of your talk, its ordering and content. What helps is to have a script for your session and speaker notes. Do not ever read your notes while speaking! This is a path to disaster. Update your speaker's notes based on feedback received and review them before the session starts to remember the important points you wanted to highlight. </p>
<h2>#3 Know your audience and engage with them from the beginning</h2>
<p>I have to confess that with this one I don’t have a good experience with virtual events. Getting feedback in the virtual presentation is much harder and I’ll mention it later. Knowing your audience is important to better position your talk but also it gets the audience more engaged. To connect with your audience, you should ask the room what they want to hear. Ask the audience about their background, expertise in the subject, biggest challenges, and listen to what they have to say. This will make your session more dynamic, tailored to your audience and the audience will have the bonding with you that you talk about what they want to hear. It’s absolutely fine to make adjustments to your speech based on the comments you hear. Skip slides if you have to, prepare backup slides that you can use for a more technical audience. This will make your presentation less disconnected and more fun. </p>
<h2>#4 Get comfortable with your setup</h2>
<p>Especially with virtual events, it’s important to make sure your setup works - this includes microphone, camera but also an ability to switch displays if needed while screen sharing, switch from slides to your demo, etc. In the case of the live event, take advantage of things like a clicker and practice running your talk with it, make sure your computer works well and avoid any unfortunate surprises during the live event. Whenever possible, practice using the equipment and setup in which you’ll be giving the talk. In the case of virtual talk, record your session and check the quality of your microphone from the recording. A quality microphone for a few $$$ might be a significant improvement to your talk. If you decide to have your camera on (which I can recommend for a more engaging presentation), check your background (your light, your camera pointing in the right direction, and not to the ceiling, etc.). Those small changes can make a big difference. </p>
<h2>#5 Record your demos and share your slides</h2>
<p>Always record your demos! I’ve been bitten many times by issues with the internet, a weird conference setup, or other circumstances that forced me to use my pre-recorded session.  Anything can happen and having a backup available can save you from unnecessary stress. Also, pre-recorded demos and slides can be shared and used for marketing purposes. Either for marketing your project in other media and channels or even when you apply for a talk at a different conference. Sharing slides and your demos also adds to your credibility and allows the audience to come back to your examples, links and other content. </p>
<h2>#6 Differentiate and add value</h2>
<p>You’ve seen many talks about Subject X on the internet already. Feels like everybody is talking about the same and your talk is just yet another one of the subjects? Then think about how to differentiate from others - provide examples based on your personal experience, focus on a specific area and topic where you’re strongest, focus on feedback you’ve received from other users, customers and colleagues. What worked for me was to give the audience content that they could use the very same day. Give the audience something they can try and see results immediately, let them experience the impact of what you’re talking about. When you do so, your audience will trust you and come back to you in the future for more since they’ve been able to reproduce easily what you’ve shown them.</p>
<h2>#7 Ask for questions and get feedback</h2>
<p>Keep the audience engaged and either offer the audience to ask questions during your session or let them know about a dedicated time for questions at the end of your session. The questions part is important as it also offers your feedback on your session. Did the audience get the point of your talk? Did they understand your examples? Do they know how to follow up? With virtual conferences, you use polls. Some questions might require more time and deeper analysis, so make sure you give them a way to connect with you even after the conference. Offer the audience a way to get detailed answers (over a chat, in a booth or even by sharing your email) while keeping your response brief and very specific to the question asked. If helps to provide evidence with facts, examples to support your answers. And it’s absolutely OK to be honest when you don’t know the answer rather than to bluff. You can offer to find the answer and post it on your social media to create further engagement. </p>
<p>Lot of people will never do any public speaking due to lack of confidence and fear. But like many other things, public speaking is a skill that can be trained, developed and eventually mastered with enough practice. My first (few) talks were very nervous and I can’t say I was proud about how I handled them, but I definitely learned from them. Over the years, I gained more confidence but I still invest a lot of time into getting myself prepared for the talk and do all the tips mentioned above. As you speak more, you’ll improve and your first time experience can’t stop you from getting better. Good luck with your talk, and don’t forget: Practice makes perfect!</p>    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>/cz/blog/submitting-a-proposal-for-devconf-cz-2022</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="/cz/blog/submitting-a-proposal-for-devconf-cz-2022" />
    <title>Submitting a proposal for DevConf.CZ 2022</title>
    <published>2021-10-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2021-10-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Dorota Volavkova</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">DevConf.CZ has always welcomed first-time speakers as well as seasoned pros. If you&#039;re a first-time speaker or just want to make sure you learn as much as possible before submitting a proposal, you&#039;re at the right place! We&#039;re going to cover all you need......</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p>DevConf.CZ has always welcomed first-time speakers as well as seasoned pros. If you're a first-time speaker or just want to make sure you learn as much as possible before submitting a proposal, you're at the right place! We're going to cover all you need to know to get your proposal accepted at DevConf.CZ 2022.</p>
<h2>Don't miss the deadline</h2>
<p>First and foremost, make sure you submit your proposal on time and sooner rather than later. <strong>The DevConf.CZ 2022 Call for Proposals ends on October 24, 2021 EOD.</strong> We always remind the date on our <a href="https://twitter.com/devconf_cz">social media channels</a> and you can also make sure you have the latest information on <a href="https://www.devconf.info/cz/">our website</a>. </p>
<h2>Make it relevant and engaging</h2>
<p>DevConf.CZ 2022 is built around <a href="https://www.devconf.info/cz/#themes">a list of themes</a> we believe are attractive for attendees as well as speakers but we're also open to other high-quality talk suggestions. We are interested in technical sessions and speakers who are not afraid to dive deep into details of the area of their interest. Sessions with a lot of audience interactions and demos are highly encouraged. We're not looking for an overview or high-level topics. Make sure to avoid product pitches and marketing presentations.</p>
<p>Those with a keen eye for detail might have noticed the crystal ball in DevConf.CZ logo. The motto of the conference is “<strong>#define future</strong>” and the future is what we're interested in. We'd like to see emerging topics that might hit mainstream engineering in 1-2 years. Talking about new and upcoming work generally increases your chance of acceptance.</p>
<h2>Select the right session type</h2>
<p>Since we're a hybrid event in 2022, we made a few changes in the session types to adjust to the new format based on what we’ve learned from past conferences and virtual events. While we will stick to talks, workshops and meetups. We want to make sure the content is focused, tells the whole story, and is structured in a way that allows engagement for both in-person and virtual audiences.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Talk (25 minutes)</strong> - A talk is where you present with slides and demos to an audience. We recommend reserving some time in the end for Q&amp;A, e.g. a 20-minute talk and a 5-minute Q&amp;A. Feel free to recruit your colleagues to interact with people in chat while you are talking. A talk has one primary speaker, optionally another (secondary) speaker. It should be bite-sized and focused on a certain topic. This means that you should not expect to be able to cover multiple broad areas in one talk. You can submit more than one proposal, to cover a set of topics, but we cannot guarantee their final scheduled order. Therefore, we recommend you submit topics that are independent and do not need to be presented in a specific order.</li>
<li><strong>Deep dive talk (50 minutes)</strong> - A deep dive talk is the same as a talk, but this is considered a two-part session (you will talk during two 25 minute time slots). You should consider that different audiences may join each part due to different timing of parallel talks in other rooms and tailor the content accordingly. This option is recommended for deep technical dives that include a demo.</li>
<li><strong>Discussion (50 minutes)</strong> - A discussion is where you lead/moderate a conversation with a group of knowledgeable panelists who answer prepared questions or questions from the audience as selected by you for appropriateness to your topic and session goal. It is an interactive session and you’re asked to engage with the audience during the session.</li>
<li><strong>Lightning talk (5 minutes)</strong> - A lightning talk is a short presentation focused on getting people interested in something new. The goal of the lightning talk is to convey key information in a clear and concise manner. You can talk about things that excite you, challenges you overcome, or insights into your work that you wish you knew before you started.</li>
<li><strong>Workshop (60 minutes)</strong> - A workshop is a hands-on demo where you and other workshop leads interact with each other and with audience members on chat, sharing your knowledge and experience on a focused topic. The goal of a workshop is to teach or practice a skill. You should not expect the audience to follow each step of the workshop live, however, they should have all necessary instructions if they wish to. As a result, workshops should be actionable and goal-oriented. We allow up to three active presenters in a workshop. You must designate one of them to be the primary session leader. We give in-person workshop leads a choice to decide whether they want to stream the content online. If yes, it is up to you to cover both channels and we recommend you recruit your colleagues to interact with people in chat while you are talking.</li>
<li><strong>Meetups</strong> - Meetups are open to all participants, they serve as a place for open discussions during a dedicated time, sharing the latest project developments and interaction with contributors and attendees. Meetups are organized as virtual chat rooms or in-person meetings. Meetups are either 25 or 50 minutes long, although we will consider exceptions.</li>
<li><del><strong>Booths</strong></del> - Based on our experience from last year and possible capacity limitations at the venue, we decided we will <strong>NOT</strong> have booths. We encourage everyone who would normally set up a booth to submit a meetup proposal instead.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Do you need help with your submission?</h2>
<p>If you still aren't 100% certain about your proposal we invite you to the DevConf.CZ 2022 CfP office hours on <strong>Thursday, October 21 from 3 - 5 PM CEST</strong> on our <a href="https://discord.com/invite/devconf">discord channel</a>. You can discuss your proposal or get some tips from session reviewers and past DevConf.CZ speakers.</p>
<p>You can also join the <a href="https://discord.com/channels/785879296379453491/844640981319024670">#CfP-help</a> discord channel and chat with event organizers about anything related to CfP anytime or take a look at following <a href="https://www.devconf.info/assets/files/devconf-cz-cfp-tips.pdf">presentation</a>.</p>    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>/cz/blog/reimagining-conference-topics-and-what-we-hope-for</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="/cz/blog/reimagining-conference-topics-and-what-we-hope-for" />
    <title>DevConf.CZ 2022: Reimagining conference themes and what we hope for</title>
    <published>2021-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2021-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Dorota Volavkova, Radek Vokal</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">It feels like DevConf.CZ 2021 has just ended and we are already preparing for next year&#039;s event. For DevConf.CZ 2022, we are aiming for a hybrid conference, with both an in-person and a virtual presence to ensure that everyone who wishes to participate......</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p>It feels like DevConf.CZ 2021 has just ended and we are already preparing for next year's event. For DevConf.CZ 2022, we are aiming for a hybrid conference, with both an in-person and a virtual presence to ensure that everyone who wishes to participate is able to do so.</p>
<h2>What we know so far</h2>
<p>We will stick to our usual dates at the end of January and our usual venue, the Faculty of Information Technology at Brno University of Technology. We are currently discussing all the possibilities with the faculty and we are very excited to return to a familiar venue.</p>
<p>These are the plans, however we can plan all we want but we still don't know what January 2022 is going to look like. We are prepared to adapt along the way. All we know for sure is that we will organize DevConf.CZ again, we are looking for speakers, we will welcome attendees and we will celebrate volunteers that make the conference happen. It’s not going to be easy, but hey, this is DevConf, we love trying new things and experimenting!</p>
<h2>Fewer themes; more focus</h2>
<p>Speaking of experiments, we’ve decided to reimagine our conference themes for DevConf.CZ 2022. Over the last several years, DevConf.CZ has amassed a long list of conference themes, which we developed over time through discussions with various communities, Red Hatters and other open source contributors outside the company. We’ve received feedback that as the number of themes has grown, the conference has gotten way too broad and spread in too many directions. It is exhausting to attend (and run) a 3-day conference with 12 thematic tracks, often running in parallel, especially in a virtual environment.</p>
<p>For 2022, we’ve chosen to pare down the list of themes to better focus on current trends in the software and hardware industry. We want to focus on the sorts of topics that we all keep hearing about, but that we wish we could explore in more depth.</p>
<p>We plan to open a Call for Proposals with the new set of themes, and include in our schedule only those that receive enough quality submissions. We may keep some of the topics for the future because we believe DevConf.CZ has reached a level of maturity that will allow us to rotate the focus of the conference every year. This will hopefully help us to structure the hybrid conference more effectively and keep it focused on current and emerging trends.</p>
<h2>What could you present?</h2>
<p>This is the updated list of conference themes and what we envision would fit into them:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Cloud &amp; Hyperscale</strong> - Topics around Kubernetes, quantum computing, high availability, *aaS, anything that powers large data centers or small private clouds, best practices for development, and operations at scale, resource efficiency, etc.</li>
<li><strong>Future Tech and Open Research</strong> - What’s next? Any topics that are currently being discussed or actively researched yet their impact is still potential. Best practices and great examples of open source research collaborations are welcome.</li>
<li><strong>Edge Computing</strong> - Modern embedded systems, microcontrollers, management of embedded systems, infrastructure for embedded systems, resource optimization, peripherals, tools, and edge in automotive are some of the topic ideas appropriate for this track.</li>
<li><strong>HPC, Big Data and Data Science</strong> - High performance systems, data storing and processing, best practices for data lakes/data mesh, and parallelism and vector computing.</li>
<li><strong>Open Source UX/Design</strong> - Open source practices for UX and UIs, Design Thinking, Service Design, UX and Customer Experience. How to get users and customers involved in software design and other best practices.</li>
<li><strong>Open Source Education</strong> - Improving how students learn—and how instructors teach— withOpen Source. Open Source tools that facilitate education, as well as the overall education community that operates in an open source way (MOOC's, free bootcamps, university relations, etc).</li>
<li><strong>Modern Software Development</strong> - Trending topics from software development, application modernization, new trends, microservices, distributed computing and continuous improvement. Development of secure code, code validation and verification.</li>
<li><strong>Analysis, Testing and Automation</strong> - Embedded intelligence in products for automation, IoB - internet of behaviours, analytics and automated remediation capabilities, risk and change analysis, AI powered orchestration, and machine learning in analysis and test automation (i.e, test failure analysis, test generation, and test selection).</li>
<li><strong>Linux distribution</strong> - Firmware, Linux kernel, base platform for containers, desktop, Silverblue, and upgrades.</li>
</ul>
<p>Think about what you’d love to talk about and how it can fit into these themes. We are always seeking technical sessions and speakers who are not afraid to dive deep into details of the area of their interest.</p>
<p>If you feel like your session does not fit into any of these themes, do not hesitate to submit a proposal and let us know why you think it is worth discussing. We drafted the list of themes we believe are attractive for attendees as well as speakers, but we will find space for all high quality talks.</p>
<p>Submit your proposals at <a href="https://cfp.devconf.info/">https://cfp.devconf.info/</a> by October 24, 2021.</p>    ]]></content>
</entry>
    </feed>
